CURRENT POSITION

Postdoctoral Associate, Cornell University

2021 - present

Supervisor: Kirstin Petersen, Collective Embodied Intelligence Lab

Department: Electrical and Computer Engineering

Interim PI: I was honored to serve as interim Principal Investigator for the Collective Embodied

Intelligence lab as part of the NSF Career Life Balance program, from August through October 2022. Primary responsibilities included supervising research progress of four

PhD students and planning weekly group meetings.

EDUCATION

University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign (UIUC)

2015 - 2020

Degree: Ph.D. in Computer Science

Thesis Title: Designing Boundary Interactions for Simple Mobile Robots

Committee: Steven M. LaValle (advisor), Nancy Amato, Sayan Mitra, Todd Murphey (Northwestern

University)

Colorado School of Mines (CSM)

2011 - 2015

Degree: B.S. in Engineering Physics. GPA 3.93/4.0

Minor in Computational and Applied Mathematics Minor in Public Affairs, McBride Honors Program

PUBLICATIONS

Journal Articles

- 1. **A. Nilles**, Y. Ren, I. Becerra, S. M. LaValle. "A Visibility-Based Approach to Computing Nondeterministic Bouncing Strategies," in *The International Journal of Robotics Research*, 2021.
- 2. A. LaViers, C. Cuan, C. Maguire, K. Bradley, K. B. Mata, **A. Nilles**, I. Vidrin, N. Chakraborty, M. Heimerdinger, U. Huzaifa, R. McNish, I. Pakrasi, and A. Zurawski. "Choreographic and Somatic Approaches for the Development of Expressive Robotic Systems," in *MDPI Arts*, 2018.

Conference Articles

- 3. J. A. Defay, **A. Nilles**, and K. Petersen. "Characterization of the Design Space of Collective Braitenberg Vehicles," in the *16th International Symposium on Distributed Autonomous Robotic Systems (DARS)*, 2022.
- 4. **A. Nilles**, S. Ceron, N. Napp, and K. Petersen. "Strain-Based Consensus in Soft, Inflatable Robots," in the *IEEE 5th International Conference on Soft Robotics (RoboSoft)*, 2022.
- 5. S. Ceron, M. A. Kimmel, **A. Nilles**, and K. Petersen. "Soft Robotic Oscillators With Strain-Based Coordination," in *IEEE Robotics and Automation Letters (RAL)*, 2021.
- 6. **A. Nilles**, A. Pervan, T. Berrueta, T. Murphey, S. M. LaValle. "Information Requirements of Collision-Based Micromanipulation," in the *14th Workshop on the Algorithmic Foundations of Robotics (WAFR)*, 2021.
- 7. M. Suomalainen, **A. Nilles**, S. M. LaValle. "Virtual Reality for Robots," in *IEEE Conference on Intelligent Robots and Systems (IROS)*, 2020.
- 8. **A. Nilles**, J. Wasserman, A. Born, C. Horn, J. Born, S. M. LaValle. "A Hardware and Software Testbed for Underactuated Self-Assembling Robots," in the *IEEE International Symposium on Multi-Robot and Multi-Agent Systems (MRS)*, 2019.
- 9. A. Nilles, Y. Ren, I. Becerra, S. M. LaValle. "A Visibility-Based Approach to Computing Nondetermin-

- istic Bouncing Strategies," in the 13th Annual Workshop on the Algorithmic Foundations of Robotics (WAFR), 2018.
- 10. **A. Nilles**, C. Gladish, M. Beckman, and A. LaViers. "Improv: Live Coding for Robot Motion Design," in *Proceedings of the 5th International Conference on Movement Computing (MOCO)*, ACM. 2018.
- 11. **A. Nilles**, I. Becerra, and S. M. LaValle. "Periodic Trajectories of Mobile Robots," in *IEEE Conference on Intelligent Robots and Systems (IROS)*, 2017.

Workshop and Poster Presentations

- A. Nilles, K. Petersen. "Design of Scalable, Robust Robotic Collectives with Embodied and Stigmergic Coordination," in *Collective Intelligence: Foundations + Radical Ideas Symposium & Short Course* at the Santa Fe Institute, June 2023.
- A. Nilles, S. M. LaValle. "Robust Combinatorial Planning over Simple Boundary Interactions," in Workshop on Robust Task & Motion Planning at RSS 2019.
- A. Nilles, D. A. Shell, J. M. O'Kane. "Robot Design: Formalisms, Representations, and the Role of the Designer," in *Workshop on the Autonomous Design of Robots* at ICRA 2018.
- A. Nilles, I. Becerra, and S. M. LaValle. "Controllable Billiards: Characterizing the Paths of Simple Mobile Robots," poster in *Dynamics Days*, 2018.
- A. Nilles, "Partially Coherent Transport: Computational Analysis and Overcoming Anderson Localization," 2014 CSM Physics poster session.
- A. Nilles, "Teaching the Smart Grid: Why Data Management is Essential to the Future of Electricity," Washington Internships for Students of Engineering Journal of Engineering and Public Policy.

INVITED TALKS

- "Agent-Environment Interactions for Uncertainty Reduction and Communication", Microsoft Future Leaders in Robotics and AI: Celebrating Diversity and Innovation Seminar Series, Maryland Robotics Center, University of Maryland, 24 February 2023, recording available on MRC YouTube Channel.
- "Is Less More? Characterizing resource trade-offs for simple mobile robots with embodied intelligence." Autonomy Talks, Institute for Dynamic Systems and Control, ETH Zürich. 8 February 2021, recording available on ETH Zürich Frazzoli YouTube Channel.
- "Is Less More? Characterizing Resource Trade-offs When Designing Robot-Boundary Interactions." Cornell Robotics Seminar, 12 May 2020, talk given via Zoom.
- "Towards Self-Assembly and Collective Manipulation with Extremely Underactuated Robots," NxR Group Meeting, Northwestern University. 1 March 2019.
- "Interesting Trajectories of Mobile Robots in Polygons," 2017 Midwest Robotics Workshop (MWRW). May 18 2017.
- "New Developments in Combinatorial Data Structures and Algorithms for Robotic Planning, Filtering and Design," UIUC Theory Seminar, October 3 2016.
- "Case Studies in Robotics Toolchains," UIUC Robotics Seminar, September 9 2016.

AWARDS AND HONORS

Cyber-Physical Systems Rising Star (34 selected of 117 applicants)	2023
Microsoft Future Leader in Robotics and AI, Maryland Robotics Center	2023
Cornell Postdoc Leadership Program	2021-2022
Mentor Stipend, Illinois Scholars Undergraduate Research Program	2019
Leung Student Venture Fund Award, UIUC ECE Department	2019
IEEE MRS (Multi-Robot Systems) Travel Grant	2019
• Workshop on Algorithmic Foundations of Robotics (WAFR) Robot Guru Travel Grant	2018

Saburo Muroga Endowed Fellowship, UIUC CS Department	2015-2016
 Physics Faculty Distinguished Graduate Award, CSM 	May 2015
 Leo Borasio Outstanding Junior Award, McBride Honors Program, CSM 	May 2014
President's Undergraduate Scholarship, CSM	2011-2015

TEACHING EXPERIENCE

UIUC Teaching Assistant

July-December 2019

- One of five TAs for ECE 470: Introduction to Robotics (90 students)
- Class topics included state estimation and filtering, forward and inverse kinematics, motion planning, control, and introductory computer vision.
- Individually supervised a twice-weekly 15-student lab section, using Universal Robots UR3 robot arms and computer vision.
- Gave two 75-minute guest lectures on inverse kinematics for the full ninety-student class.
- Developed homework and test problems using the online learning platform PrairieLearn.

Colorado School of Mines Math Learning Center

Description: Tutored five hours a week for all classes in Math department. Primarily calculus,

differential equations, and linear algebra.

Dates: Jan 2015 - May 2015

North American Network of Science Labs Online (NANSLO)

Description: Developed, monitored, and troubleshot remote-controlled robotic physics, chemistry,

and biology experiments for college students in online classes. Served as a TA and equipment technician while classes were running. This was innovative distance learning

research funded through the Department of Labor.

Dates: Feb 2012 - May 2014

PROFESSIONAL SERVICE

• Reviewer for IROS, ICRA, CGTA, RA-L, T-RO, MRS, Nature Communications

- Publication Chair for DARS 2024
- Co-organizer for ICRA full day workshop, "Compositional Robotics: Mathematics and Tools," held virtually in 2021, hybrid in 2022 and 2023.
- Co-organizer for ICRA full day workshop, "Robotics and Art: Automating Expressions," hybrid workshop, 2022.
- Co-organizer for Robotic Science and Systems (RSS) full day workshop, "Minimality and Trade-offs in Automated Robot Design." July 16 2017.
 - Recruited and communicated with speakers, helped develop The Robot Design Game, facilitated workshop and discussions.
- President of Computer Science Graduate Students Organization (2017 2018), member 2015 2020.
 - Organized social events, discussed and advocated for graduate student needs, planned logistics and cultural events for annual prospective PhD student visit weekend.
- Head of student committee organizing an semester-long internal Robotics@UIUC seminar (Fall 2016).
 - Recruited student speakers, advertised weekly talks, maintained wiki.

OUTREACH AND DIVERSITY SERVICE

- 2019-2020: Mentor for Illinois Scholars Undergraduate Research (ISUR) Program. Supervised two URM undergraduate students in robotics research.
- 2019: WAFR Robot Guru Mentor six month remote mentorship of undergraduates interested in

robotics research

- 2014: Founding member of Equality Through Awareness (ETA) at CSM, a group promoting student well-being and diversity in STEM through discussion, mentoring, and invited speakers.
 - I facilitated weekly group reading club discussions on understanding issues faced by underrepresented groups in STEM
 - In 2018, ETA was awarded the Martin Luther King Jr. Recognition Award from CSM
- 2012-2015: Society of Physics Students, CSM participated in outreach events such as interactive physics demonstrations at local elementary and middle schools.

OTHER EMPLOYMENT

Petronics internship: Development of small, agile mobile robot

Description: Worked closely with engineers to develop hardware and software for their mobile

platform. Configured a ROS server and added a wifi module to the robot to stream data through ROS. Analyzed the resulting data using Python, to compare streaming pose estimates from the robot with a ground truth from a motion capture system (also ROS-integrated). Analyzed how the robot slipped on different surfaces to help improve

low-level controllers.

Dates: May 2016 - August 2016

Complexity Sciences Center, UC Davis

Description: NSF REU with Dr. Jim Crutchfield. I successfully implemented an information-theoretic

learning algorithm for exploratory robots with limited sensing capabilities. I also

researched ways to include more memory in the learning algorithm.

Dates: June - Aug 2014

Institute of Electrical and Electronics Engineers (IEEE)

Description: Washington Internships for Students of Engineering (WISE) program: researched smart

grid data management and policy alternatives; published an overview and policy recom-

mendation.

Dates: June - Aug 2013

MENTORING

- Elizabeth Garner (2021-2023)
 - undergraduate, assisted
- Steven Ceron (2021)
 - Ph.D. student, I advised on signal processing and algorithmic approach to FoamBot platform
- Emily Hall and Max Altman (2019-2020)
 - 4th year undergraduates: I supervised on a funded undergraduate research project (a robotic pen), assisted with project transition during onset of pandemic
- Jordan Parker (2018)
 - 1st year undergraduate, she developed Improv features and trained on user study
 - connected with a paid research position in the RAD Lab
- Chase Gladish (2018)
 - 4th year undergraduate: I supervised her senior thesis on Improv, a live-coding platform for robot motion
 - co-author on 2018 MOCO paper
- Samara (Yingying) Ren (2017-2020)
 - undergraduate: co-author on one WAFR paper and IJRR paper, until she started a graduate

degree at EPFL

- Austin Born, John Born, Chris Horn, Justin Wasserman (2017-2019)
 - supervised team of undergraduates, recieved \$1000 undergraduate research award from ECE department
 - published 2018 MRS paper
 - J. Wasserman wrote senior thesis on "Controlling, Modeling, and Scaling Underactuated, Nondeterministic Robot Structures"
- Michael Zeng (2016)
 - 3rd year undergraduate: collaborated on dynamical properties of bouncing robots
- Oluwami Dosunmu-Ogunbi (2015-2016)
 - 4th year undergraduate: worked on CAD, microcontrollers, IMU data collection and analysis
 - Advised on graduate school applications resulting in a Ph.D. appointment with Jessy Grizzle at University of Maryland.

REFERENCES

- Professor Steven M. Lavalle
 Center for Ubiquitous Computing
 University of Oulu, Oulu, Finland
 steven.lavalle@oulu.fi
 +358 294 482807
- Professor Kirstin H. Petersen
 Electrical and Computer Engineering, College of Engineering
 Cornell University, Ithaca, New York, USA
 kirstin@cornell.edu
- Amy LaViers
 The Robotics, Automation and Dance Lab amy@theradlab.xyz
 https://theradlab.xyz
- Professor Sayan Mitra
 Department of Electrical and Computer Engineering
 Coordinated Science Laboratory
 Affiliate Professor, Department of Computer Science
 University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign, USA
 mitras@illinois.edu
 (217) 333 7824
- Professor Nancy Amato
 Department of Computer Science
 University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign, USA namato@illinois.edu
 (217) 333 3426